Does AI have a hidden debt problem?
That's a question that's been
circulating the past couple of months
amid reports that some of the biggest
tech companies in the world have acred
over $1 trillion in quote hidden debt
borrowings that they managed to keep off
of their balance sheets. With these
companies being the big five AI
hyperscalers, the companies building the
data centers to power these models,
Alphabet or Google, Amazon, Meta,
Microsoft, and Oracle. Now, the AI
spending spree has already been subject
to plenty of skepticism and scrutiny.
OpenAI itself has single-handedly
committed to over $600 billion in
spending by 2030. Their accusations of
circular financing deals with Nvidia and
other players. And companies that had
previously been money printers have
quickly become money furnaces, burning
cash faster than your Studio Ghibli
prompts have been burning GPUs. But the
concern now is that with these companies
needing to raise so much money for this
spending, they've started to accumulate
a bunch of debt. And rather than just
doing so regularly, some have started to
enter complex ownership structures for
the single purpose seemingly of moving
some of these borrowings off of their
balance sheet to make them harder to
find. Uh so I thought, you know what
would be fun for today's video? You know
what would be a real hoot? Let's go
through these companies filings, compile
all of these offbalance sheet items into
a nice simple spreadsheet, and review
the numbers together as a class so we
can better understand the company and
category breakdown of these amounts.
Because given all the hoopla, it might
be a bit confusing. We're seeing this $1
trillion figure thrown about. This
article talks about $3 trillion. And
while these articles do often give some
description of what these amounts are
when you're only seeing the headline
figure circulate, it can be hard to
grasp what this actually represents. So,
I figured today I'd take the time to go
through just that, compile all the
numbers into one place, and give a
better picture of what the so-called
hidden obligations are. And I say
so-called because while it is true that
these amounts don't necessarily show up
on the company's balance sheet, and that
seems to be intentional in some cases,
they're not exactly hard to find. In
fact, each of these companies has an
explicit commitments or contractual
obligations section in their filings
that lists out all these details.
Nonetheless, I thought I'd do some of
the leg work and put everything in one
place just to make it easier to
understand where these companies sit. Uh
now because we're diving into the
financials of these companies, I do have
to disclose uh that from a personal
holding standpoint, I do have exposure
to all of these companies in some way,
including direct ownership of Meta,
Google, and Microsoft stock. I don't
like to talk about my personal holdings,
but in this case, it's appropriate to
share that since, you know, that could
add bias to the information I share. But
the goal here is not to provide an
investment recommendation, but just to
highlight a risk that's important for
anyone to understand. if they own these
stocks, which is pretty likely given
that they're basically in every major US
index fund out there. But with that out
of the way, let's start with the debt
that is reported on these companies
balance sheet. And here it's important
to understand that historically, with
the one exception of Oracle here,
really, big tech companies in the US
have typically had pristine balance
sheets with very minimal borrowing and
so much free cash flow generation that
they often had more cash on hand than
they needed. Today, with the AI spending
spree, debt has started to creep higher,
but the balance sheets for these
companies are still relatively healthy.
I've listed out some of the key details
here from the company's latest filings.
The periods are as of June 30th for
every company except Oracle, which has a
year end of May 31st, and I've made some
minor adjustments for announcements that
have come out since then. For example,
Alphabet actually issued $25 billion in
corporate bonds after its latest filing.
So, I've added that very conservatively
only to the debt side of the balance
sheet figures here. Uh, just again to be
very conservative. And I've colorcoded
any number that's been altered. But
otherwise, this is how things looked as
of their latest reports. And the first
thing I'll point out is that two of the
companies, Alphabet and Microsoft,
actually have negative net debt balances
inclusive of recent bond issuances and
leases on the balance sheet. Meaning
theoretically these companies could net
out their borrowings with the cash they
have on hand if they chose to do so.
Meanwhile, for the companies with a
positive net debt balance, meaning that
they've borrowed more money than they
have cash on hand, uh the net debt to
income ratios across different measures
are all still fairly small. Oracle is
one exception here where their debt is
more substantive. You can see the ratios
when you compare their debt to equity
and other income figures are all much
higher than the other companies here.
But for the other four companies,
they're in fairly good positions. The
debt to equity ratios are all at or
below the sector average for the US
information technology sector, which
sits at 0.51
times. Net debt to income is very low
for each of the different profit
measures. And the interest coverage
ratio here shows that these companies
can pretty easily cover the cost of
their debt many times over with the
expense representing a small fraction of
their total revenues. Now mind you,
interest expenses are accelerating. I
actually annualized the latest quarterly
figure for more accurate run rate
amount. But even with that, two of the
companies have negative net interest
expenses, meaning that they earn more
interest on the cash they have on hand
than they pay with their debt. Now, one
important caveat is that with these
companies spending so much of the money
they earn in future investments, they
don't actually have that much cash left
over if they were to say try to pay off
their debt uh because they're being so
aggressive with their growth. But
nonetheless, you can see that their
balance sheets paint a fairly muted debt
picture. Yes, debt balances as a whole
are increasing, but when compared to
profitability and other measures, it's
fairly manageable. But what about the
offbalance sheet measures? Well,
generally speaking, the companies have
three or four different categories of
offbalance sheet items that we're seeing
referred to by a lot of these articles
that highlight this $1 trillion plus
figure of hidden debt. Non-cancable
contractual commitments, funding and
construction commitments, unccommenced
leases, and financial back stops and
guarantees with that last category being
the most controversial here. The first
category, non-cancellable contractual
commitments, as the name implies, are
legal obligations to buy some sort of
good or service in the future. Uh the
explicit makeup varies by company, but
they generally include the same uh three
or so items. The first being components
for data center infrastructure such as
semiconductors. Uh because companies
like Nvidia have seen such strong demand
for their supply of chips. uh these
companies have entered purchase
agreements into the future to ensure
that they can get the chips they need
for uh their business. Secondly, there's
power purchase agreements to supply
power for these data centers which
oftent times the companies have to enter
these long-term take or pay arrangements
whereby they pay for the electricity
whether they use it or not in order to
incentivize the power provider to make
the investments necessary to supply the
amount of electricity that they need
given that they need so much here. And
finally, there's third-party cloud
capacity, meaning that they're basically
renting compute power for AI models from
other companies. Again, for similar
reasons to the first two items, to
ensure that they have the supply
basically they need for their own
businesses. Now, as the name suggests,
these agreements are legally binding.
But the reason they don't show up as a
liability on the company's balance sheet
is that the supplier has yet to provide
their end of these arrangements. There's
been no good or service delivered. So by
standard accounting rules, you don't yet
realize that liability or expense. They
will eventually show up once the
contract is actually actioned, but for
now it's just a disclosure in the
financial filings for these companies.
So just how much have these companies
committed to spending here? Well, quite
a lot with the five companies altogether
committing to over $1.5 trillion of
spending with this amount being
predominantly for the buildout of AI
data centers. Yes, there might
technically be some other line items
included that are involved with the
normal businesses of these companies,
but when you compare it to 5 years ago,
it's a fraction of the current amount.
So, it's safe to say that this massive
step up is mostly related to AI, which
would also align with the details
provided in the disclosures. Now, in
terms of these obligations, not all
companies are created equal. Alphabet by
far has the largest amount at over $800
billion in spending commitments uh
followed by Meta at around $350 billion.
And as a percentage of total assets, you
can see that these two companies are
standouts with them basically committing
the majority of their total assets to
these future spending obligations. So
that's the first major offbalance sheet
item and it's a doozy. Uh the second
category could technically be thrown
into this first one but I decided to
segregate it out uh with it being
funding and construction commitments
which similarly rather than just buying
uh goods and services revolves around
investing or building out uh related to
investment commitments that they have.
These may be related to joint ventures
the companies are a part of whereby they
are obligated to spend and invest a
certain amount or for example with
Microsoft they're invested in open AI
and might have different funding
obligations there and these are at times
contingent on the company in question
meeting a certain benchmark but I still
think they're worth including in our
analysis of potential obligations. You
can see that they are smaller amounts
than the contractual commitments at
around $100 billion cumulatively across
the five companies, but it's still a
material amount. Then there's the third
category, which is also a sizable one
that a lot of these articles seem to be
drawing particular attention to, which
is unccommenced leases. uh lease
agreements that these companies have
entered but because they have not yet
commenced therefore some point uh some
starting point in the future they are
not yet showing up on the company's
balance sheet which again is standard
accounting practice but nonetheless
moves a lot of these obligations into
the disclosures. Now leases as you might
be aware generally have two different
forms. There are either financial
leases, which like a mortgage, involve
making regular payments to use and
eventually own the asset in question, or
in this case, most of these appear to be
operational leases, whereby you're just
agreeing to rent something over time and
make regular payments for the right to
use that asset. In this case, oftentimes
data center space. However, many
analysts still view operational leases
as a debt-like liability, given that
they're legally binding. If you miss a
payment, there can be consequences
similar to if you defaulted on a debt
payment. And these companies have plans
to substantially increase the lease
agreements that they are involved with.
Across the five companies, there are
again over $1 trillion in unccommenced
lease obligations, which would more than
double their current total debt
obligations inclusive of leases of
around $700 billion. and again
represents a good chunk of these
companies total assets with Meta and
Microsoft having the largest dollar
amounts here at over $300 billion in
future leases. So already you can see
why these amounts are concerning. These
companies are committing themselves to
spending hundreds of billions of dollars
in the AI buildout for an area that has
yet to really prove its long-term
financial viability. But the final
offbalance sheet item, financial
guarantees and backs stops, is arguably
the most concerning given that it's
absolutely fair to argue that this is
where debt is actively being hidden. Uh
you see, some of these companies have
set up variable interest entities or
special purpose vehicles, VIEs and SPVS
respectively, that operate as separate
businesses and are accounted for under
the equity method. To oversimplify,
these companies will set up these VIEs
so that they themselves own less than
50%. So they have substantial influence
but not a controlling ownership share of
these businesses. And because of that
they can account for the VIE under the
equity method whereby they don't add the
assets and liabilities of that company's
balance sheet to their own but rather
just summarize the entire value of that
business as essentially one line item in
their own balance sheet in the asset
section. And companies like Meta, for
example, have used the structure to
raise debt in these VIs without that
debt showing up on their own balance
sheet. Uh, for example, over the past
few years, Meta has been co-developing a
major data center project in Louisiana
called Hyperion, one of the largest data
center projects in the world with an
estimated cost of over $50 billion. The
data center project is owned by an SPV
called Benet Investor, named after the
famous French pastry from the region,
which Meta owns 20% of. And in October
of 2025, the SPV raised $27.3
billion in one of the largest corporate
bond issuances on record. Now, this data
center is being built entirely for Meta.
They will be the sole lease of this
property starting in 2029. But so far,
all of this could be argued to make
strategic sense. Meta might want a new
massive data center, but might not want
to be in the business of operating and
owning a massive data center. So, they
set up this separate business. it
becomes the owner and operator of the
data center. They lease from that
company and the business is the one to
take on the debt so that Meta themselves
doesn't get in trouble if that company
defaults on its payments. But here's the
thing. In order to raise this debt for
the SPV, Meta provided a residual value
guarantee for the SPV's debt for the
entire amount of the bond issuance. In
other words, while the debt is
technically owned by the SPV, Meta is on
the hook if they miss a payment to their
bond holders. And given that Meta is the
sole lease of this campus, they are the
only source of revenue for the SPV to
make these bond payments for this debt.
A very elaborate and likely intentional
move to shift the company's debt off of
its balance sheet. And the thing is
they've already done it again for a
different project in El Paso, Texas,
where the company has entered a joint
venture with Black Rockck for an SPV
called Soapia Investor to build another
data center. With this SPV having
already issued its own $12.3 billion in
secured nodes that again have been
backed by Meta. So you can see why all
this set off the alarm bells for quite a
few people. Yes, all these details are
technically found in the company's
financial filings. And there might be
some other valid reasons for setting up
an SPV here, but it does really just
seem like a stunt to make the company's
debt harder to find. Yes, some of the
offbalance sheet items could be argued
to not technically translate into debt.
But when combined with the lease
payments that are being used to pay for
the debt borrowed by these SPVS, these
companies are in a roundabout way still
taking out debt technically in their own
name when they have these guarantees.
So, how bad is the situation really?
Well, the thing is it's really just Meta
and Google with sizable obligations
here. I've summarized the financial
guarantees here. In Meta's case, I've
included a 14.7 contingent purchase
commitment since I view that as a
financial guarantee. And you can see
that while Oracle itself does have $3.3
billion of similar guarantees, Meta and
Alphabet have guaranteed debts in the
tens of billions, which yes, is less
than the other line items, but is still
material. But all these numbers can be
hard to contextualize. The real question
is can these companies handle these
obligations
and that's a very hard question to
answer and will depend on who you ask. I
will say that regarding the hidden debt
sort of accusations.
It is to an extent being blown out of
proportion. There is a real story here
of Meta transferring its debt off of its
balance sheet. But when combined with
stories of over1 trillion dollars in
hidden debt, it can sort of lead to this
perception that all five of these
companies are hiding hundreds of
billions of dollars of these types of
guarantees. When in reality, it's really
just two of them with guarantees under
$100 billion, an amount that as a
percentage of revenue and assets is
material. But that's assuming the
company takes the full amount on the
chin. And if they did, they could
technically cover it with less than one
year of earnings. Meanwhile, around the
larger off-balance sheet items, there
are a number of considerations there as
well, with one of the big ones being
that these aren't directly equivalent to
debt. Yes, they do represent contractual
liabilities that come with risk, but in
the same way that from a personal
budgeting standpoint, you wouldn't add
all of your future phone payments, uh,
rent, and, you know, other subscriptions
as a debt balance that you owe. These
are amounts that the company has
committed to paying but that they get
some good or service for that they've
estimated they will need at some point
in the future anyway. Which brings us to
a very important second point which is
that these amounts aren't present values
which is how they are typically reported
once they reach the balance sheet. Uh
meaning they represent the nominal sum
of all future payments but those future
payments aren't discounted depending on
how far in the future they are. meaning
that the timing of these payments can
make or break how intensive this
liability is. For Meta's roughly $350
billion in unccommenceed leases, for
example, this amount represents payments
for agreements that start through 2036
and have terms ranging from one year to
30 years in the future. Needless to say,
$350 billion owed tomorrow versus $350
billion owed over 30 years starting 10
years from now, very different scenarios
in terms of how feasible of an expense
that is. Now, the issue is we don't have
all the details explicitly laying out
when these obligations come due. Uh
there are tidbits here and there
specifically for what's due in kind of
the next year or so. Uh but the point is
that these amounts are in a way
overstating what these obligations are
in present value terms. So again,
they're not equivalent to the total debt
balance that you see on the balance
sheet. But let's say you want to add
these amounts to the total debt balances
anyway to see how it affects their
credit ratios. How do things look? Well,
not good when compared to historical
standards, right? We do see the ratios
deteriorate quite a bit. I'm adding
everything but the financial guarantees
since they're mostly related to the
leases anyway and arguably would be
captured by those amounts. And to be
clear, these are not accurate
representations of the company's debt
situation. But if you do this crude
update, it does cause the debt ratios to
jump. However, one important
consideration is that higher debt
balances are typical for traditional
data center companies. We can look at
Equinex for example, which is a pure
play data center company. And we'll take
their financials from 5 years ago before
all of this AI stuff. You can see that
their debt ratios are actually
comparable to the big tech companies
when you're adding in these lease and
spending commitments to their debt
balances. Again, Oracle is a bit of an
outlier here with the weakest financial
position. But compared to other data
center companies, these ratios aren't
all that outlandish. So, it could be
graciously argued that as these
companies are entering more into the
hyperscaler space, it's expected that
their balance sheet would follow suit.
And while the speed of it reaching that
point is obviously concerning with
hundreds of billions of dollars being
spent and raised every year, it
nonetheless would be typical for a data
center company to have higher debt
levels. However, that's not to say that
this doesn't represent real risk. AI
data center companies are different from
traditional data centers where at times
space and electricity are really the
only things being provided. And right
now it seems really attractive to enter
the data center space given the
unprecedented demand for compute
capacity and the premiums being paid for
that you know supply. But that might not
always be the case as we see this
buildout of the infrastructure. And the
issue is that these companies are moving
from a capital expenditure light sort of
asset light model to a very capital
expenditure and asset heavy business
model that from a profit standpoint is
much less attractive. And whether you
view it as debt or not, any sort of
fixed payment obligation increases risk
for the company when revenues can
fluctuate higher and lower. So it's
absolutely fair to argue that the risk
profile for these big tech companies is
certainly deteriorating. These companies
have moved from the pristine balance
sheets to having very intensive assets
that require a lot of maintenance. In
the past, the nice thing about companies
like Meta was that if their projects
like Metaverse were a flop, they could
always pivot. They could abandon if need
be. And while there could be a cost with
that, they could always move forward.
With these commitments, though, that's
no longer really an option. This really
does seem to represent a point of no
return where these companies are full
steam ahead on AI whether it works out
or not, whether these AI businesses are
sustainable or not. And that makes them
a lot less nimble should things change
in the future. Now, naturally, this is a
gamble these companies seem to be
comfortable with. They have a lot of
high expectation for AI demand into the
future that seemingly makes this all
worth it. But so far, a lot of this
buildout outside of capital raises has
been funded by the traditional highly
profitable businesses of these
companies. Meaning, we have these
companies locking into long-term
liabilities with yet to be proven, but
likely short-term revenues to service
those obligations. A stark contrast to
how these companies have operated
historically, which has made a lot of
investors nervous. Now, as I mentioned
at the beginning, this is not an
investment recommendation one way or the
other. This is one aspect of these
businesses that we've dove into. There
are other aspects that could justify
this risk being taken on. Uh but it's
nonetheless something that I think is
worth being aware of if you invest in
these companies. Especially because
while these obligations may be
manageable today, they could continue to
grow from here. For example, do the
spending commitments represent the
majority of these companies capital
expenditures in the near future? Are
they additional to the capital
expenditure trend that's already been
eating up all of these companies free
cash flow? And what about revenue? Do we
see revenue quickly fill in at a speed
fast enough to make these commitments
worth it? We just don't know yet. We
don't have the answers for all of these
questions. So, how companies move
forward from here will be really
important. Nonetheless, those are the
figures as they stand today, and we'll
just have to wait and see what happens.
Thanks for joining me. I hope you found
this video helpful. If you did, please
do make sure to like, subscribe, all
that good stuff. It does help the
channel tremendously. And let me know
your thoughts down below about the AI
hidden debt situation. If you think it's
overblown, underblown, you know, fair.
Any and all thoughts, welcome down
below. Thanks again for joining me. And
as always, be safe out